Hey, Leonard, check this out.
Leonard, regarde ça.
Leonard, she's doing it again.
Leonard, elle recommence.
I think it upsets Sheldon when you play with the food.
Sheldon n'aime pas quand tu joues avec la nourriture.
No, it upsets Sheldon when she willy-nilly takes it from the containers...
Non. Sheldon n'aime pas quand elle se sert
...without regard for its equitable distribution.
sans se soucier d‘un partage équitable.
This is essentially why you have famine in India.
Voilà l'origine dela famine en Inde.
You want me to put it back?
Tu veux que je le repose ?
-Leonard? -lt upsets Sheldon...
- Leonard ? - Sheldon n'aime pas
...when you play with the Sheldon.
qu'on joue avec le Sheldon.
What's up, my nerdizzles?
Quoi de neuf, les intellos ?
Raj, Sheldon, I want you to meet my girlfriend, Bernadette.
Je vous présente ma copine, Bernadette.
-Hello. -Leonard, Penny.
- Salut. - Leonard.
-You know my girlfriend, Bernadette. -Yeah. Hey.
- Ma copine, Bernadette. - Salut.
Bernadette, say "fo'shizzle" to my nerdizzles.
Dis ”salut" à mes potes.
I don't think I can.
Impossible.
I don't have Howard's street cred.
Je ne suis pas aussi branchée qu'Howard.
I hope it's all right, I told Bernadette she could join us for dinner.
Je lui ai dit qu‘elle pouvait manger avec nous.
-Sure. The more, the merrier. -No, that's a false equivalency.
- Plus on est de fous, plus on rit. - Faux.
More does not equal merry.
Un fou ne rit pas.
If there were 2000 people right now, would we be celebrating?
Si on était 2 000 ici, on rirait ?
No, we'd be suffocating.
Non, on suffoquerait.
-Sheldon. -Don't "Sheldon" me.
- Sheldon. - Arrête.
-We ordered for five people, not six. -lt's fine.
- On n‘a pas commandé pour six. - Ça va.
We'll put it on the table, family-style.
On partage comme en famille.
Oh, sure. Why don't we put our hands behind our backs...
Et si on mettait les mains dans le dos
...have an old-fashioned eating contest?
pour faire un concours de rapidité ?
Relax. It'll be fine. Sit down, you guys.
Détends-toi. Ça ira. Asseyez-vous.
ALL EXCEPT BERNADETTE: No. -What?
- Non. - Quoi ?
Oh, yeah, you can't sit there.
Ne t‘assieds pas ici.
-Why not? -That's where Sheldon sits.
- Pourquoi ? - C‘est la place de Sheldon.
He can't sit somewhere else?
Il s'assied ici ?
In the winter, that seat's close enough to the radiator...
L'hiver, il est assez près du radiateur
...so he's warm yet not so close that he sweats.
pour avoir chaud sans transpirer.
In the summer, it's in the path of a breeze...
L'été, il est dans une brise
...created by opening windows there.
créée par ces fenêtres—là.
It faces the television at an angle that isn't direct so he can talk...
L‘angle de la télévision n‘est ni direct
...yet not so wide that the picture looks distorted.
ni trop ouvert pour éviter une distorsion de l'image.
Perhaps there's hope for you after all.
Ton cas n‘est pas si désespéré.
-I love your shoes. -Oh, thanks. They are cute, aren't they?
- J‘adore tes chaussures. - Elles sontjolies.
-Where'd you get them? -Shoes for Less.
- D'où ? - Chaussures-pas-chéres.
-l've been meaning to go over there. -Oh, great selection, great prices.
- Je veux y aller. - Beaucoup de choix et pas cher.
My mother was right. Hell is real.
Ma mère avait raison. L‘enfer existe.
Come on, Sheldon, let the women-folk chat.
Allons ! Laisse parler les femelles.
Women-folk?
Les femelles ?
Gals? Chicks?
Les nanas ? Les poulettes ?
Utero-Americans?
Les Utéro-Américaines ?
-Just eat your dinner. -Don't take him too seriously.
- Mange. - Ne le prends pas au sérieux.
A lot of what he says is intended as humor.
Il fait beaucoup d‘humour.
Yeah, well, I don't think it's very funny.
Je ne trouve pas ça drôle.
Me neither, but he just lights up when I laugh.
Moi non plus. Mais il aime quand je ris.
Howard, never let her go.
Ne la laisse jamais partir.
Leonard, Howard says you're working on fundamental tests...
Leonard, tu travailles sur des tests fondamentaux
-...of quantum mechanics. -I am. Are you interested in physics?
- en mécanique quantique ? - Tu aimes la physique ?
I find it fascinating.
C‘est fascinant.
lfl hadn't gone into microbiology...
Sans la microbiologie,
...I probably would have gone into physics or ice dancing.
j'aurais fait de la physique ou du patinage artistique.
My tests of the Aharonov-Bohm quantum interference effect...
Mes tests sur l‘effet Aharonov-Bohm
...have reached an interesting point.
sont prometteurs.
We're testing phase shift due to electric potential.
On teste le décalage de phase.
-That's amazing. SHELDON [CHUCKLES]: Yes.
- C‘est épatant. - Oui.
Leonard's work is nearly as amazing as third graders...
Son travail est aussi épatant qu'un CE2
...growing lima beans in wet paper towels.
qui fait pousser des haricots sur des serviettes humides.
While I appreciate the "oh, snap"...
J'apprécie Ie : ”Bien dit."
...l'm uncomfortable having your moist breath in my ear.
Mais j'ai horreur de sentir ton souffle humide.
Are you going to try to set up the voltages using tunnel junctions?
Tu vas essayer de fixer la tension électrique ?
Yes, I am.
En effet.
-Wanna see a simulation on my laptop? -Oh, yeah. Show me.
- Tu veux voir une simulation ? - Montre-moi.
In microbiology, the most exciting thing I get to work with is yeast.
En microbiologie, l‘objet d‘étude le plus passionnant est la levure.
SHELDON: Howard? -Yeah?
- Howard ? - Oui.
Your shoes are delightful.
Tes chaussures sont splendides.
Where did you get them?
Où les as-tu achetées ?
-What? -Buzzinga. I don't care.
- Quoi ? - Je m'en fiche.
Ha-ha. Eat my dust, racially stereotypical plumber.
Dans les dents, petit plombier racialement stéréotypé.
That's not fair. I got stuck behind a tree.
J‘étais coincé derrière un arbre.
And a cow and a penguin.
Et une vache et un pingouin.
Face it, dude, whether it's a real car or a virtual cartoon car, you can't drive.
Admets-le. Voiture Virtuelle ou réelle, tu ne sais pas conduire.
-Just need a little more practice. -What you need is cheat codes...
- J'ai besoin d‘entrainement. - Tu as besoin
...motor skills and a genie who grants wishes...
de codes secrets et d'un génie qui accorde
...to little boys who suck at "Mario Kart."
des vœux aux nuls à “Mario Kart".
Sheldon, can I talk to you for a second?
Je peux te parler, Sheldon ?
It's not about shoes, is it?
Pas au sujet de chaussures ?
I don't think I could go through that again.
Je ne pourrais pas revivre ça.
-lt's not about shoes. -Then speak.
- Non. Pas de chaussures. - Parle.
Go away.
Va-t'en !
I agree, it's rude, but she asked for privacy.
Oui, c‘est impoli. Mais elle a dit “en privé".
Thanks, Raj. Okay, so here's the thing.
Merci, Ra]. Écoute-moi.
l was wondering if you could maybe teach me a little physics.
Pourrais-tu m‘enseigner un peu de physique ?
-A little physics? -Yeah.
- Un peu de physique ? -Oui.
There's no such thing. Physics encompasses the entire universe.
Absurde ! La physique englobe l'univers.
From quantum particles to supernovas.
Des particules quantiques aux supernovas.
From spinning electrons to spinning galaxies.
Du spin des électrons aux galaxies.
Okay, cool, I don't need the PBS special.
On n‘est pas sur la chaîne scientifique.
I wanna know enough so I can talk to Leonard about his job.
Je veux en savoir plus pour parler avec Leonard.
Like Bernadette does.
Comme Bernadette.
-Why can't Leonard teach you? -Because I wanna surprise him.
- Tu as demandé à Leonard ? - C‘est une surprise.
Can't you surprise him in some other way?
Surprends-le autrement!
For example, I'm sure he'd be delightfully taken aback if you clean your apartment.
Par exemple, il serait ravi que tu nettoies ton appartement.
Come on, Sheldon, this is important to me.
Allez ! C‘est important.
This would be a massive undertaking...
La tâche serait colossale
...and my time is both limited and valuable.
et mon temps est précieux et limité.
You're sitting here playing video games all day.
Tu joues toute la journée.
Okay, point.
Un point pour toi.
What sort of foundation do you have?
Quelles bases as-tu ?
Did you take any science classes in school?
Tu as suivi des cours de science ?
Sure. I did the one with the frogs.
Celui avec les grenouilles.
It was pretty cool. A lot of the girls threw up, I gutted that thing like a deer.
C‘était génial. Plein de filles ont vomi. Moi, je l'ai éventrée.
No. I'm sorry, Penny. I don't think so.
Désolé, Penny. Ça ne va pas être possible.
Oh, come on, a smart guy like you? It'll be a challenge.
Intelligent comme tu es ? Ce sera un défi.
You could make it like an experiment.
Tu pourrais en faire une expérience.
Interesting.
Intéressant.
I suppose if someone could teach sign language to Koko the gorilla...
Si quelqu'un peut apprendre la langue des signes à Koko le gorille,
...I could teach you some rudimentary physics.
je peux t‘apprendre la physique.
Great. It's a little insulting, but great. I'll be Koko.
Super. Un peu insultant mais super. Je serai Koko.
Mm. Not likely. Koko learned to understand over 2000 words.
Pas vraiment. Koko a appris 2 000 mots.
Not one of which had anything to do with shoes.
Pas un seul ne concerne les chaussures.
Hey, fellas, this is my girlfriend, Bernadette.
Salut, les gars. C‘est ma copine, Bernadette.
My girlfriend, Bernadette.
Ma copine, Bernadette.
-Who are all those people? -l have no idea.
- Qui sont ces gens ? - Je l‘ignore.
-Hey, Leonard. -Hi.
- Salut, Leonard. - Salut.
Look, it's Howard and his girlfriend, Bernadette.
Howard et sa copine, Bernadette.
Thought I'd give the little woman a tour of the old salt mines. Heh.
Je veux lui faire Visiter les mines.
He doesn't mean salt mines. He means where he works.
Il ne parle pas de mines, en fait, mais de son lieu de travail.
Yeah, no, I got it.
J‘avais compris.
-So how's your experiment going? -Terrific.
- Ton expérience avance ? - C‘est génial.
Getting the electron accelerator set up. We should be ready day after tomorrow.
L'accélérateur d‘électrons est presque prêt. On la fait après—demain.
-Boy, I'd love to see that. -You're welcome to come.
- J'aimerais voir ça. - Tu es la bienvenue.
Really? That'd be great.
Vraiment ? Ça serait super.
How exciting is that?
Comme c‘est excitant!
Like Hanukkah in July.
Comme Hanoukka en juillet.
Do they have that?
Ça se fait ?
This isn't non-fat yogurt. This is fatty-fat fat.
Ce n‘est pas un yaourt allégé. C‘est grassement gras.
Excuse me.
Excusez-moi.
-Could you grab me another napkin? -Sure.
- Prends—moi une serviette. - D‘accord.
Thanks, honey.
Merci, chérie.
All right. What is your deal?
Bon, tu nous fais quoi la ?
Excuse me?
Pardon ?
Inviting my girlfriend to come see your electron accelerator?
Tu invites ma nana à venir voir ton accélérateur ?
Yeah, so?
Oui. Et alors ?
Wow, you really are a piece of work.
Tu ne manques pas de culot!
It's not enough you get the prom queen...
La reine du bal ne te suffit pas.
...you have to get the head of the decorating committee too?
Il te faut aussi la chef décoratrice ?
-What are you talking about? -Look, don't play innocent with me.
- De quoi tu parles ? - Ne fais pas l‘innocent.
l practically invented using fancy lab equipment to seduce women.
C‘est moi qui ai inventé la drague au laboratoire.
-Has it ever worked? -Not so far, but that's not the point.
- Ça marche ? - Pas vraiment. Ce n‘est pas la question.
Howard, relax. lam not interested in your girlfriend.
Détends-toi. Elle ne m‘intéresse pas.
I hope not, because you don't wanna mess with me.
C‘est mieux comme ça. Tu ne veux pas avoir affaire à moi.
I'm crazy.
Je suis un fou.
I believe you.
Je te crois.
SH ELDON: Research journal, entry one.
Article de recherche, note une.
I'm about to embark on one of the great challenges of my scientific career:
Je suis sur le point de relever le plus grand défi de ma carrière :
teaching Penny physics.
enseigner la physique & Penny.
I'm calling it Project Gorilla.
Je l‘appelle Projet Gorille.
-Hey, Sheldon. -Come in. Take a seat.
- Salut, Sheldon. - Entré. Assieds-toi.
Subject has arrived.
Le sujet Vient d‘arriver.
I've extended a friendly, casual greeting.
J‘ai échangé des salutations amicales.
Ready to get started?
Prêt à commencer ?
One moment.
Un moment.
Subject appears well-rested and enthusiastic.
Le sujet semble reposé et enthousiaste.
Apparently, ignorance is bliss.
Apparemment, l‘ignorance est signe de bonheur.
All right, let us begin.
Trés bien. A nous deux.
-Where's your notebook? -Um, I don't have one.
- Où est ton cahier ? - Je n'en ai pas.
How are you gonna take notes without a notebook?
Comment veux-tu prendre des notes ?
l have to take notes?
Prendre des notes ?
How else are you gonna study for the tests?
Pour préparer les tests.
-There's gonna be a test? -Tests.
- Il y aura un test ? - Des tests.
Here. It's college-ruled. I hope that's not too intimidating.
Tiens. Comme à l‘université. J'espère que ça ne t‘effraie pas.
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
- Merci. - De rien.
Now, introduction to physics.
Introduction àla physique.
Yo-- What is physics?
Qu'est—ce que la physique ?
Physics comes from the ancient Greek word physika.
"Physique" Vient du grec “physika".
It's at this point that you'll wanna start taking notes.
Tu dois commencer à prendre des notes.
Physika means the science of natural things.
"Physika" signifie : science dela nature.
And it is there in ancient Greece that our story begins.
Et c‘est en Grèce antique que notre récit commence.
Ancient Greece?
- En Grèce antique ? - Lève la main pour poser une question.
It's a warm summer evening, circa 60!) B.C.
C‘est une chaude nuit d'été, 60!) ans avant J.-C.
You've finished your shopping at the local market or agora.
Tu as fini tes courses au marché local, l'agora.
And you look up at the night sky.
Et tu regardes le ciel.
And there you notice some of the stars seem to move...
Tu remarques que certaines étoiles bougent.
...so you name them planetes or wanderer.
Alors, tu les appelles "planetes" ou ”voyageur".
Yes, Penny?
Oui, Penny?
Does this have anything to do with Leonard's work?
Ça a un rapport avec le travail de Leonard ?
This is the beginning of a 2600-year journey we're going to take together...
C‘est le début du voyage de 2 600 ans que nous allons faire ensemble,
...from the ancient Greeks through Isaac Newton to Niels Bohr...
depuis les Grecs, en passant par Isaac Newton,
...to Erwin Schrodinger...
puis par Erwin Schrädinger
...to the Dutch researchers that Leonard is currently ripping off.
pour arriver aux chercheurs néerlandais que Leonard plagie.
-Twenty-six hundred years? -Yeah, give or take.
- 2 600 ans ? - Plus ou moins.
As I was saying, it's a warm summer evening in ancient Greece--
Comme je le disais, c‘était une chaude nuit d'été…
-Yes, Penny. -l have to go to the bathroom.
- Oui ? - Je dois aller aux toilettes.
-Can't you hold it? -Not for 2600 years.
- Ça ne peut pas attendre ? - Pas 2 600 ans.
SH ELDON: Project Gorilla, entry two.
Projet Gorille, note deux.
I am exhausted.
Je suis épuisé.
-Howard? -Uh-- Huh?
Howard ?
It unhooks in the front.
Ça se dégrafe devant.
Oh, that explains a lot.
Tout s‘explique.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: Howard, I'm home.
Howard, je suis rentrée!
Of course.
Évidemment.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: Senior fitness was canceled.
Le cours de gym a été annulé.
It turns out you can forget how to ride a bike.
Apparemment, le Vélo, ça peut vraiment s'oublier.
I'm fine, but, oy, did Sam Harpootian eat gravel.
Je vais bien mais Sam Harpootian a mangé le béton.
That's great, Ma.
C‘est cool, maman.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: What's great about an 80-year-old Armenian man...
En quoi c‘est cool qu'un Vieux de 80 ans
...with half his chin scraped off?
s‘égratigne la moitié du menton ?
-I guess I should go. -No, don't move.
- Je devrais y aller. - Non.
Hey, Ma, can I have lamb stew for dinner?
Maman, tu me fais un ragoût d'agneau ?
MRS. WOLOWITZ: Lamb stew? I'd have to go to the supermarket.
Un ragoût ? Je vais devoir aller au supermarché.
Please? I got a real hankering.
S'il te plaît ! J'ai une envie qui me tenaille.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: Oh, I can't say no to my little tushy-face.
Je ne peux rien refuser à mon petit Face-de-popotin.
-l'll be back soon. -Thanks, Ma.
- Je reviens. - Merci, maman.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: Do you want the regular peas or the Le Sueur?
Tu veux des petits pois normaux ou doux ?
Always Le Sueur peas with lamb stew.
Toujours des doux avec le ragoût.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: You're right. When you're right, you're right.
Tu as raison. Quand tu as raison, tu as raison.
-What if they're out of the Le Sueur? -Then get the regular!
- S'il n‘y a pas de doux ? - Prends des normaux.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: All right. You don't have to yell.
D‘accord. Pas besoin de hurler.
Sorry about that.
Désolé pour tout ça.
-Let me just put that on vibrate. -l'm already on vibrate.
- Je le mets sur vibreur. - Je suis déjà sur vibreur.
Okay, now, that one I got.
Je l'ai comprise, celle-là !
Howard, did you say something to Leonard about me?
Tu as parlé de moi à Leonard ?
What do you mean?
Comment ça ?
He says if I go see his experiment tomorrow, it might weird you out.
Il dit que si je vais à son expérience, ça te dérangera.
Really? He said that?
Il adit ça?
-You're not jealous of Leonard, are you? -Me? No.
- Tu n'es pas jaloux de Leonard ? - Moi ? Non.
I may have mentioned that it's a little inappropriate...
J'ai dû mentionner que c‘était un peu déplacé
...to be asking another man's girlfriend to his experiment...
d‘inviter la copine d'un autre à son expérience
...without discussing it with said man.
sans en parler à son copain.
I need to ask your permission to hang out with Leonard?
Je dois te demander la permission de le voir ?
I didn't say anything like that. I said Leonard has to ask my permission.
Je n'ai pas dit ça. C‘est Leonard qui doit me demander la permission.
Come on, I don't wanna eat lamb stew with my mother.
Reviens. Je ne veux pas manger de ragoût avec ma mére.
Damn. Was this close on the bra.
J‘étais à deux doigts d‘enlever son soutif.
Now, remember, Newton realized that Aristotle was wrong...
Rappelle-toi, Newton a compris qu'Aristote se trompait,
...and force was not necessary to maintain motion.
qu‘une force n‘était pas nécessaire.
So let's plug in our 9.8 meters per second squared...
Disons que nos 9,8 mètres par seconde carrée
...as A and we get force-- Earth gravity.
sont "a". La force, soit la gravité de la terre,
--equals mass times 9.8 meters per second per second.
est égale àla masse fois nos 9,8.
So we can see that MA equals MG and what do we know from this?
Donc, "ma" égale ”mg". On en déduit que…
Oh, is that where Fig Newtons come from?
Ça Vient de lui, les gâteaux Fig Newton ?
No, Fig Newtons are named after a small town in Massachusetts.
Non, c‘est le nom d‘une Ville dans le Massachusetts.
-No, don't write that down. -Sorry.
- N‘écris pas ça. - Désolée.
Now, if MA equals MG...
Donc, si "ma" égale ”mg",
-...what does that imply? -I don't know.
- ça implique ? - Aucune idée.
What--? But--? How can you not know? I just told you.
Comment ça ? Je Viens de te le dire.
Have you suffered a recent blow to the head?
Tu as reçu un coup sur la téte, récemment ?
Hey, you don't have to be so mean.
Pas la peine d'être méchant.
I'm sorry. Have you suffered a recent blow to the head?
Désolé. Tu as reçu un coup sur la téte, récemment ?
No. You just suck at teaching.
Non. Tu es nul comme prof.
Really? Of those two explanations, which one seems the most likely?
De ces deux explications, laquelle est la plus plausible ?
Oh, God.
Mince!
Sheldon, look, I'm trying to understand but you're going too fast.
J'essaie de comprendre mais tu vas trop Vite.
-Can you just back up a little bit? -All right.
- On peut revenir en arrière ? - D‘accord.
It's a warm summer evening in ancient Greece--
C‘est une chaude nuit d'été, dans la Grèce antique...
Not that far back.
Pas si loin.
Okay, at what point did you begin to feel lost?
A quel moment as-tu cessé de suivre ?
I don't know. Where were we looking up at the night sky?
Je ne sais pas. Quand a-t-on regardé le ciel ?
-Greece. -Damn it.
- En Grèce. - Bon sang !
Look, there's no need to get frustrated.
Ne sois pas frustrée.
People learn at different rates.
Chacun apprend à son rythme.
Unlike objects falling in a vacuum, which...?
Contrairement aux objets qui tombent dans le vide qui...
MA equals MG?
”Ma" égale "mg" ?
-Squared? -No.
- Au carré ? - Non.
-Aristotle?
- Aristote ?
-Five? -Oh!
Cinq ?
-Why are you crying? -Because I'm stupid.
- Pourquoi tu pleures ? - Car je suis stupide.
Well, that's no reason to cry.
Ce n‘est pas une raison pour pleurer.
No, one cries because one is sad.
On pleure quand on est triste.
For example, I cry because others are stupid and it makes me sad.
Je pleure, car les autres sont stupides et ça me rend triste.
Look, can we just please forget about all this extra stuff...
Est-ce qu'on peut oublier ces trucs
...and can you just tell me what Leonard does?
etjuste parler du travail de Leonard.
All right.
D‘accord.
Leonard is attempting to learn...
Leonard essaie de comprendre
...why subatomic particles move the way they do.
le déplacement des particules subatomiques.
Really? That's it? Well, that doesn't sound so complicated.
Vraiment ? C‘est tout ? Ça parait simple.
It's not. That's why Leonard does it.
C‘est pour ça que Leonard travaille dessus.
Okay, I just have one question.
J'ai juste une question.
What exactly are subatomic particles?
C‘est quoi les particules subatomiques ?
-A good question. -Thank you.
- Bonne question. - Merci.
And to answer it, we first must ask ourselves, "What is physics?"
Pour y répondre, interrogeons-nous sur la physique.
Oh, balls.
C‘est pas vrai !
It's a warm summer evening in ancient Greece.
C‘était une chaude nuit d‘été dans la Grèce antique.
Okay, I got a bone to pick with you.
On a des comptes à régler.
What did I do now?
Quoi encore ?
l was in bed with Bernadette and you text-blocked me.
J‘étais avec Bernadette. Ton SMS m‘a empêché de conclure.
-What? -Yeah, we were completely naked...
- Quoi ? - Nous étions nus,
...and about to devour each other when:
prêts à nous jeter l'un sur l'autre, quand :
You text her that l have a problem with her hanging with you.
Tu as dit que je ne voulais pas que tu la voies.
You do have a problem with her hanging out with me.
Tu ne veux pas que je la voie.
But that's not what you tell her.
Tu ne devais pas lui dire.
-What was I to tell her? -I don't know.
- Je devais dire quoi ? - Je ne sais pas.
Something that doesn't make me come off as a petty, jealous douche.
Un truc qui ne me fait pas passer pour un sale type.
And what would that be?
Du genre ?
Come on, do I have to think of everything?
Est-ce que je dois penser à tout ?
Hey, Leonard, am I too late to see your experiment?
Salut. Je n'arrive pas trop tard ?
-Oh, hi. -Hi.
- Salut.
-What are you doing here? -Same thing you're doing here.
- Que fais-tu la ? - La même chose que toi.
-Came to see Leonard's experiment. -No, you didn't.
- Je suis venu pour l‘expérience. - C‘est faux.
You said Leonard's experiment was stupid.
Tu as dit qu'elle était nulle.
You told her my experiment was stupid?
Tu lui as dit ça ?
l was just repeating what Sheldon said.
J'ai juste répété les mots de Sheldon.
Look, let's not get off topic. Bernadette, I need to apologize.
Revenons à nos moutons. Je suis venu m'excuser.
You know, I was wrong to tell you who you should be friends with.
J'ai eu tort de te dire quels doivent être tes amis.
-Should I leave you two alone? -No, Leonard, you should hear this.
- Je vous laisse seuls ? - Non. Tu dois écouter ça.
Okay, good. Because I wasn't really gonna go.
Bien. Je ne voulais pas vraiment partir.
Look, I know I come off as confident and worldly...
Je sais que j'ai l‘air sûr de moi et expérimenté,
...but the truth is I'm not.
mais c‘est faux.
We're shocked.
Quel choc !
Which is why I tend to feel threatened by other guys.
C‘est pourquoi je me sens menacé par les autres types.
Or loud noises, clowns and nuns.
Ou par les bruits forts, les clowns et les normes.
But I now realize how foolish that is.
Je me rends compte que c‘était idiot.
He had a panic attack once when he got his head stuck in a sweater.
Il a fait une crise d'angoisse quand sa tête s‘est coincée dans son pull.
It was a full turtleneck.
C‘était un col roulé.
-And why aren't you helping me? -I don't know.
- Tu ne m'aides pas ? - Non.
Maybe because I'm crazy?
Je suis un fou.
Bernadette, please, I'm asking you to give me another chance.
S'il te plaît, donne—moi une autre chance.
What do you think, Leonard? Should I give him another chance?
Qu'en penses—tu, Leonard ? Je la lui donne ?
It's up to you. He didn't call your experiment stupid.
A toi de voir. C‘est mon expérience qu'il a traitée de nulle.
Come here, tushy-face.
Viens—lè, Face-de-popotin.
Tushy-face. That is going on Twitter right now.
Face-de-popotin. Je vais mettre ça sur Twitter.
Raj, you should've seen Leonard's experiment.
Raj, tu aurais dû voir son expérience.
The interference pattern was cool when the electron beam was on.
Le diagramme d'interférence était super.
I'm glad you enjoyed it. Most people aren't that interested in what I do.
Ravi que ça t'ait plu. Personne ne s‘intéresse à mes travaux.
Actually, that's not true, Leonard.
C‘est faux, Leonard.
I've been thinking that, given the parameters of your experiment...
Vu les paramètres de ton expérience,
...the transport of electrons through the nano-fabricated rings...
le transport des électrons à travers les anneaux
...is no different than the experiment already conducted in the Netherlands.
ne diffère pas de l'expérience menée aux Pays-Bas.
Their observed phase shift in the diffusing electrons inside the ring...
Le décalage de phase lors du passage des électrons
...already demonstrated electric analogue...
a prouvé l'équivalent électrique
...of the Aharonov-Bohm quantum interference effect.
de l‘effet Aharonov-Bohm.
That's it. That's all I know.
Voilà. C‘est tout ce que je sais.
Oh, wait.
Un instant!
Fig Newtons were named after a town in Massachusetts, not the scientist.
Les Fig Newton tiennent leur nom d‘une Ville et non de Newton.
[ENGLISH - US - SDH]
[FRENCH]